## **YOUMING LIU**

### Senior Fullstack Developer

+1 585 499 7876 • youmingliu39@gmail.com • linkedin.com/in/youming-liu421 • Ellenton, FL

## **Summary**

Youming has over 9 years of experience in ranging from **Web** and **Mobile development** to Optimization Problems, **Machine Learning** and **Data Science** with a strong focus on **Full-Stack** web applications. He specializes in **Python**, **Typescript**, **Django**, **Node.js**, **Express**, **Nest** and **React**, **React Native**, **Vue**, **Angular** with expertise deploying to both server and serverless environments on **AWS**, **GCP** and **Azure**. He also works with relational databases and large datasets. He is the type of developer who can quickly comprehend business requirements and turn them into valuable software.

#### Skills

Full Stack Development · Mobile Development · Android Development · iOS Development · Devops Engineering

 ${\sf Javascript} \cdot {\sf Typescript} \cdot {\sf Python} \cdot {\sf PHP} \cdot {\sf Java} \cdot {\sf Golang} \cdot {\sf Ruby} \cdot {\sf HTML5} \cdot {\sf CSS} \cdot {\sf NPM} \cdot {\sf Yarn} \cdot {\sf Vite}$ 

React · React Native · Flutter · Vue · Nuxt · Angular · Next · Gatsby · Redux · Recoil · Mobx · Zustand · Zod · Yup

SCSS · LESS · Material UI · Ant Design · Chakra UI · Styled Component · Radix UI · Shadcn · Bootstrap · Tailwind CSS

 $Node.js \cdot ExpressJS \cdot NestJS \cdot Laravel \cdot Django \cdot Flask \cdot Fast API \cdot MySQL \cdot PostgreSQL \cdot Redis \cdot MongoDB \cdot Supabase \cdot Firebase \cdot SQL \cdot PostgreSQL \cdot Redis \cdot MongoDB \cdot Supabase \cdot SQL \cdot PostgreSQL \cdot Redis \cdot MongoDB \cdot SQL \cdot PostgreSQL \cdot Pos$ 

 $\textit{Github} \cdot \textit{Gitlab} \cdot \textit{Jira} \cdot \textit{Bitbucket} \cdot \textit{CI/CD Pipeline} \cdot \textit{TDD} \cdot \textit{Jest} \cdot \textit{Cypress} \cdot \textit{Mocha+Chai} \cdot \textit{Unit Testing} \cdot \textit{E2E Testing} \cdot \textit{Jenkins} \cdot \textit{NoSQL}$ 

Amazon Web Services · Google Cloud Platform · Docker · Kubernetes · Azure · Terraform · Linux · RabbitMQ · Design Patterns

 $Stripe \cdot Mapbox \cdot Google Map \cdot Sanity \cdot tRPC \cdot gRPC \cdot Zoho \cdot Zapier$ 

# Experience

# Toptal Senior Full Stack Developer

Ellenton, FL

06/2024 - Present

- · Designed and developed a cross-browser extension with a sophisticated dashboard leveraging Plasmo, T3-stack, and PostgreSQL.
- Utilized Shadon UI for intuitive UI design, Prisma for ORM, tRPC for seamless backend communication, and TurboRepo for efficient management of microservices within a monorepo architecture.
- Championed the use of Jest, Vitest, and Cypress for rigorous unit and end-to-end testing, ensuring high-quality code and reliable software delivery.
- Led the architecture and development of Ad tech systems, implementing OpenRTB real-time bidding and VAST for Ad tags to a video player, programmatic Ad serving, and scalable tracking infrastructure using Node.js, A/B Testing and Kafka.
- · Developed and maintained Ruby on Rails applications with Salesforce API integration for seamless data synchronization.

## Fortunes Tech

Goffstown, NH

### Senior Full Stack Developer

01/2024 - 07/2024

- Led a team of 7 members while performing code review, scrum planning, writing technical documentation for newcomers and managing the tickets on the board.
- Provide the full-stack development services utilizing the Typescript, React.js, MUI, NestJS, PostgreSQL, GraphQL, Docker, AWS and TerraForm.
- · Led the UI refactoring process utilizing Material-UI, TailwindCSS and Storybook.
- Led the seamless migration from an **Express** backend with **REST API** to **Nest.js** with **GraphQL**, leveraging my advanced expertise to enhance performance, scalability, and maintainability of the application architecture.
- · Built and optimized RESTful APIs to connect Rails backend with Salesforce, ensuring smooth data flow and automation.
- Successfully orchestrated the transition from MongoDB to PostgreSQL, demonstrating advanced proficiency in database management and
  effectively optimizing the application's data storage and retrieval capabilities.
- Designed and built robust Nest backend systems by following the Serverless Architecture based on AWS Services like AWS RDS, Lambda, API Gateway, S3, SQS, SNS, Elastic Beanstalk, CloudFormation, CloudFront.
- · Led Mobile Development including Android and iOS using React Native and Expo from scratch with engineering team.

#### **Emergent Software**

St Paul, MN

10/2020 - 12/2023

#### Senior Software Developer

- · Assisted over 10 startup companies and projects with extensive knowledge of Blockchain like Ethereum network.
- Developed smart contracts for over 20 blockchain-related applications like Defi, NFT, P2E games and Metaverse projects.
- Created bot systems for blockchain transaction automation, including trading bots, arbitrage, and liquidations.
- · Created API and WebSockets endpoints for live data feeds and direct connection to the front end.
- Developed pixel-perfect, user-friendly **Web3** front end applications utilizing **React**, **Next**, **Vue** and **Angular.js** based on Figma UI/UX design and integrated with various **Solidity** smart contracts using **web3.js** and **ethers.js**.
- · Optimized gas costs for a complex multi-layer smart contract replacing solidity code with in-line assembly.
- Helped create an upgradable contract system through a **proxy** contract system.
- Oversaw and led the development of a decentralized and distributed team across four different time zones to build a full-stack application.

JOOR New York, NY

Full Stack Developer 01/2018 - 09/2020

- Designed and developed backend RESTful APIs with a diverse tech stack, including Node.js, Express, NestJS, PHP, Laravel, Python (Django, Flask), and databases like MongoDB, PostgreSQL, MySQL, and Redis, leveraging AWS and Firebase for scalable cloud solutions.
- Translated Figma, Adobe XD designs to pixel-perfect and fully responsive design using JavaScript, TypeScript and its libraries ReactJS, NextJS, Remix, Vue, Angular, HTML, CSS, SCSS, and LESS.
- Migrated a healthcare web application from the LAMP stack application to a modern MERN stack app.
- Implemented real-time communication functionalities using Web Socket and React-query.
- · Implemented Stripe API integration with payment flow, trial periods, monthly and yearly subscriptions, and withdrawals.
- · Created automated testing framework in Jest, Mocha + Chai + Simon for unit testing and e2e UI testing.
- Implemented CI/CD pipelines using GitLab Actions in each step of the development cycle which improved integration and delivery towards
  agile development methodologies.
- · Managed Salesforce data syncing with ActiveRecord, Sidekiq, and Webhook-based event triggers to keep records up to date.

Stride New York, NY Software Engineer 06/2016 - 12/2017

- Architected and developed robust, cross-browser-compatible health care front-end using JavaScript, TypeScript, React, and Next.js.
- Engineered scalable Rest APIs with Express.js, ensuring high performance and reliability.
- · Implemented advanced state management and UI styling utilizing Redux, redux-saga, and TailwindCSS.
- Designed and optimized database operations with PostgreSQL, and enforced high code quality standards using Jest for comprehensive testing.
- Spearheaded the acceleration of code delivery by introducing a Continuous Integration (CI) and Continuous Delivery (CD) pipeline, dramatically improving deployment efficiency.
- · Established and maintained scalable project infrastructures on Google Cloud Platform, ensuring optimal performance and scalability.
- Ensured project stability and reduced defects by rigorously applying TypeScript and implementing automated testing strategies with industry standard testing frameworks.

AgileEngine Boca Raton, FL
Web Developer 05/2015 - 05/2016

- Engineered and deployed robust websites leveraging PHP MVC frameworks such as Laravel and Codelgniter to ensure maintainable and scalable architecture.
- Led the planning and execution of website development, transforming design mockups into fully functional, responsive web interfaces using Angular, HTML5, CSS, JavaScript, AJAX, and JSON.
- Implemented critical security maintenance and patching protocols on website interfaces, ensuring post-launch viability and protecting against vulnerabilities.
- Developed custom **modules** and **libraries** that are highly customizable and easily reusable, enhancing development efficiency and consistency.
- Designed and transitioned legacy websites into modern, mobile-friendly platforms, utilizing responsive design techniques to create seamless user experiences across devices.

### Education

University of Pittsburgh
Master of Science - MS, Computer Science

02/2014 - 04/2015

Sun Yat-sen University

Bachelor of Science - BS, Computer Science

04/2011 - 03/2014